Uh, starting now, I will let everybody
in from the lobby. Um, and good
afternoon everybody. This is Dominic
with the New Mexico Department of
Health. And just as a reminder, these
meetings are recorded. So, please uh be
um mindful as far as language. We do
want to be able to show to ensure that
we can share these uh videos and the
recordings on the website. And so, uh,
we appreciate that. Um, and the chair,
this is the equity, access, and cultural
considerations committee, and the chair
for this meeting is, uh, Desba. And so,
with that, I will turn it over to you,
Desba.
>> Uh, good afternoon everyone. Thanks for
joining us. Um we have a great amount of
people here to uh for support and we're
so thankful for the um department of
health administrators. Um thank you for
your support in uh both electronically
and also just uh you know
psychologically thank you for being
there. Um so we have a presentation
today um in addition to um just kind of
uh other things that we might want to
look through. But this is really
important to recap from a previous uh um
meeting that we had before. We were just
really trying to set a a a baseline for
numbers. So, um, we're trying to figure
out, we have $630,000 from the equity,
uh, access, um, fund that we are trying
to figure out like how we're going to
allocate the funds to to the numerous
people in the state who, um, would need
this, um, to be able to pay for
treatments, whether the full cost of the
treatment and or partial cost of the
treatment. Cost of the treatment is
still a variable, still unknown.
Different aspects of what it would look
like to have a treatment for like say a
single mother like myself who may have a
child who needs uh child care and or
another person who may have be taking
care of an elder and also people who
might need translators or different
types of accessibility. Um what that
looks like. Um and all those factors may
or may not be considered in but right
now we were just starting from the very
very basic of establishing a baseline
and then getting to a um maximum of
where that funding would would zero out
and the person would be a patient would
be responsible for the full cost of
treatment depending on how much that is.
Now, with $630,000, we were saying it
could either be as low as 660ome people
that it might be able to offer,
depending on the cost of the treatment
to any number of like 100 or so more
people that this um money would be able
to provide um access for those patients.
Um, one of the aspects is that it's
non-reverting funds, meaning it's not
going to go back if it doesn't finish
being used at the end of the fiscal
year. It will be going into effect in
July. um of this year and then being
able to be utilized through until it
till it's depleted as far as I got from
Senator Steinborn. Um any other uh maybe
mis missings that I might have in there?
I'm sure Dominic will correct us. Um but
that's where we just kind of left off uh
last week or the last meeting is what
are we going to do? What's the baseline
for this? Um, and from there we did
establish that it was we were going to
start with looking at numbers at 200%
poverty line, federal poverty line. And
because we're looking at just the
percentages of whatever the federal
poverty line might be, because it
changes every year, changes, you know,
maybe not every year, but it changes um
depending on the economy. Um, and so
that's why we're going through
percentages. and we were capped at 600%
um where again that that money would
zero out and the patient would be
responsible for a full um full treatment
cost. Those are just where we were
starting with. We are hoping to be able
to finalize recommendations
to the board hopefully maybe by August
and have every all of the
recommendations from this committee
regarding the equity fund and or other
recommendations to the board which would
then um recommend them to uh the
department of health for consideration
into adoption. So there's a a lot of a
process. This is not the finalized um
this is what actually is going to
happen, but this is where we we were
starting from. Sorry to kind of jump the
gun again. I know we have an agenda.
Um I just kind of wanted to get
everybody up to speed on where we're at
so far in that regard. And of course we
are still um looking towards um inviting
and having uh tribal governors, the PBLO
uh governors and anyone else who are
represented with the 23 federally
recognized tribal states too um to join
in a way that they see is is good for
their for their constituents, for their
citizens um in in providing input if
they if they deem that that's what they
want to do. Um, so we're still looking
into doing that. It takes a while. Um,
respectfully.
And I think we can actually go to the
agenda.
And if there's anybody I think have any
is there anyone here that we probably
have not really
uh
anyone else who probably wants to just
kind of quickly raise their hand and say
hi if you haven't first time first time
attendee perhaps if there is anybody and
then anyone else who has been here for a
considerable time since the very
beginning. Yes, please go ahead and if
you want to say who you are because this
is also a chance for us to continue to
create uh community and network with
people. We want more people to
participate and to provide their voice
and you know two heads are better than
one. Um so if anybody wants to go ahead
and raise their hand and introduce
themselves, please go ahead and do so.
Um, we'll have Jorge or someone with the
mic
to be able to enable the mic.
>> That will be Jonathan. Thank you,
Jonathan.
>> Jonathan. Okay,
>> sweet. All right. And looks like we've
got Jim Dodson first. And just Yeah, a
reminder to everybody um else on teams.
Uh there's a icon with a hand that says
raise up at the top banner. Um and
that's how you do the raising hand. and
Jim Dodson. Um, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when ready.
And for mute, unmute. There's an icon
that says mic up at the
>> Hello,
my name is Jim. I'm a New Mexico citizen
and I've been listening in um to many of
these. I'm here representing the
elderly, disabled, and the low income.
>> Jim, I can I can barely hear you. Do you
mind maybe trying to get closer to your
mic?
>> Oh.
Um, how's that? Is that any better?
>> Yes.
>> All right. All right. I moved in a
little. So anyhow, so I I'm just here to
represent the elderly, the disabled, and
the low income. And I hope that we don't
get forgotten in this. Thank you.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Jim. And next, we've
got Siobhan Mierra.
And Siobhan, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute.
>> Hello. Um, thank you for for allowing me
to be a part of this. Uh, my name is
Siobhan, born and raised in New Mexico.
Um,
I have had my own struggles with trying
to find um, you know, help uh, with
psychedelics or plant-based medicine.
Um, I work with um, a group to try to
um, I guess represent moms and patients
in this as well. Um, so I just, you
know, I'm it's I've had my own
experience with Ibeane and with um with
ketamine and so I'm hoping that maybe
that could be useful in some of these
discussions at some point in the future.
Um, but um, yeah, it's nice to meet
everybody and I look forward in in being
a part of this group. So, thank you.
>> Awesome. Thank you, Siobhan. And next
we've got Don Moser. And Don, I've
enabled your mic. you can unmute.
>> Thank you so much. I'm Don Moser. I live
in Las Vegas, New Mexico
and I'm not affiliated with anyone and
I'm just learning a great deal and I
appreciate very much being part of the
process. I won't be able to stay long
today, but I wanted to listen as long as
I could and thank you so much.
>> Awesome. Thank you much, Don. Um, and
also for anybody who uh is able to and
wants to, uh, you can also put an
introduction or anything else into the
chat. Um, and one final reminder, yeah,
if you want to raise your hand and
speak, uh, there's that raise with a
hand icon up at the top.
>> Okay.
>> All right.
>> All right. Well, thank you all for
introducing yourselves. I know that we
have um a few of our board members who
are uh also here. I think Chris Pascusi,
I see you. And we have some regular
attendees who are also here. Thank you
so much for taking the time out of your
day to continue to be supportive to the
rest of us in this group. Um, so yeah, I
would like to just kind of go ahead and
um dive right in, but just kind of based
on what I threw at you, does anyone have
any like quick questions that may or may
not be answered by myself or Dominic?
>> No.
>> Have you I have a quick question. Is
there have you thought about working
with providers already in the space like
such as um I could throw out a name like
Dr. Wagner who's with Tranquility
Ketamine um that can possibly offer you
know services for um a lot of the people
looking for for for those type of
services and work hand in hand. So maybe
he could give like a discounted rate for
people that can afford that or that need
to pull from the funds for that.
>> So right now um in general we're this
for for for right now for this
particular um the purpose of the board
and the purpose of the psiloc medical
psilocybin is just that. Um, so if you
have I'm uh you're new to me, so I'm not
sure um if you have been able to attend
other meetings. So we do have other
meetings and maybe we can put those into
the chat as well. Um who are we have
different committees for providers,
facilitators, and we're working through
that. Um and and and again this is
strictly for medical psilocybin
regulations for that. Um we are looking
at even dosages. So, anyone who has
questions about um micro doing that's
kind of out of the purview of what we're
dealing with. It's very restricted at
this point into like the focus of what
we're doing to start um these this
program in New Mexico by the end of the
year for the beginning of of the next
year. Um so that is a great question in
terms of like for networking for the
people who are being supportive um of
the psilocybin I mean of the
psychedelics community in general um but
for the purposes of the board and the
department of health we're strictly
looking at medical psilocybin with
dosages recommending from like one gram
and above and looking at that kind of
regulation
um and then for facilitators and so
forth. That would be a different
committee. Um, and we're all at some
point we're going to be um,
you know, coming together. So, maybe it
would probably be a good idea if we
could maybe pop up the purpose of the
equity, access, and cultural
considerations if we happen to have that
slide somewhere. Um, but
>> I can get those for you.
>> Okay, great. Um, and then in the
meantime, maybe we can also have Dominic
chime in. I see that your your camera's
back up.
>> Thank you, Desba. And uh, thank you,
Siobhan. It's a great question, and we
actually have been talking to quite a
few providers. One thing to remember is
that for psilocybin services through the
program, any providers will need to go
through some training and to obtain a
permit. uh those permits as we have
already talked about in many of the
meetings um at least from the department
of health standpoint there are no fees
with regard to that. However, there may
be for the additional training that they
may have to go through which is by the
way the training is required or the
permitting I should say is required by
statute and so we will have that aspect
but we have been reaching out to quite a
few providers talking with them. There
have been many providers that have been
involved in various committees and who
have talked about the potential of
providing services at lower charges uh
or at lower fees and uh at lower costs
for individuals who need them. So, I
hope that helps. And and of course, as
we do get um the permitting rules into
place, which we're anticipating having
in place by this fall, then uh for
providers, then um we'll be continuing
to do additional outreach to see what
providers might be able to offer for
patients. So, it's a great idea, great
suggestion, and uh yes, we already have
started on some of that.
>> Perfect. Thank you for clarifying that
for me. I just have a one follow-up
question. Um, I have, you know, gone
through my own journey of, uh,
postpartum depression. I have a
three-year-old daughter. I did try to
find services in regards to trying to
get help in the psilocybin, um,
atmosphere. Um the main
um I guess the main
um situation of that why I wasn't able
to receive services was because I was on
an SSRI or mood stabilizers and the only
way to get off of those is through micro
doing. So it's kind of like a catch 22,
right? as a as a
um as a patient, if you're trying to
look to get help and get off of your
medication, there's not so there's not a
lot of help to get off of SSRIs or mood
stabilizers. And then with that being
said, you have to be off of those, like
I said, to even receive help in the
psilocybin um space. So that's kind of a
a really hard place for a lot of people
to be, right? because it a lot of people
don't want to just get off of their
SSRIs or mood stabilizers, cold turkey.
Um, and for me, the only thing that
worked was San Pedro. Um, and so I I
know a lot of people are kind of scared
to kind of go down that rabbit hole, but
that's just from my perspective and
thank you for letting me share.
>> Absolutely. And just let you know those
are some of the considerations that have
been discussed and brought up in the
dosage and administration committee. Um
because that's really where some of
those specific types of issues really
fall uh as far as for the different
aspects of developing the program.
>> Yeah. Um just to um to also chime in
there and add into that um is yeah we
you know there's there's a it's
multi-layered right now that this is
like where the government is meeting uh
the community need as well as the
research that we and the knowledge that
we already have from like the western
kind of perspective is my understanding.
This is all my opinion all my
understanding. And so while we have a
wealth of knowledge with the various
different uses of different psychedelics
and this is even going into the
synthesized ones um you know we have all
this knowledge but for the sake and the
purpose of where the government of the
state of New Mexico is at and the
purpose of what we're trying to do here
um is is really just focus it on the
medical psilocybin aspect and we might
have to um when it comes to facilitators
when it comes to providers their
knowledge may be limited to from from
from their perspective of these
different psychedelics, but the focusing
on this is just primarily a first step,
a first step for New Mexico in this
particular way. And it's not to say that
any of these other treatments and or any
other ways, dosages or otherwise, um
aren't being looked at or that they're
not important. It's just that for the
sake of this particular governmental
endeavor, this is the focus that we're
looking at medical psilocybin and where
that meets the community need. Um
especially with all of the statistics
that are going in the different aspects
of New Mexico. I'm from Rioba County.
I'm from Espanola area. Very hard-hit
community. Um it's even was even posted
in the New York um I think post recently
about there's like the one state that
has the worst uh heroin fentanyl
overdoses in the entire country and
we're constantly being looked at. Um but
you have to look at all sorts of things.
So the primary focus um right now at
this moment in this year with the board
is this particular thing. Not saying
that we're neglecting the idea of all
this other but for the for for for now
this is where we're at. Um and to go
over the purpose of the responsibilities
for the equity access and cultural
considerations committee where I'm the
I'm the chair. The purpose is to ensure
that New Mexico's medical psilocybin
services system is accessible,
culturally appropriate, and responsive
to the needs of indigenous, rural,
frontier, Hispanic, and underserved
communities that and that program
implementation promotes equity,
inclusion, and culturally grounded care
across all settings. The
responsibilities include recommend to
the board which is so this committee is
going to recommend to the bigger board
of chairpeople
board policies to expand access to rural
frontier and underserved areas in New
Mexico including but not limited to
teleaalth enabled screening and rural
training. Number two recommend
anti-discrimination
and anti-stigma policies within the
psilocyment services system. Number
three, recommend policies that ensure
culturally appropriate practices for
indigenous Hispanic communities.
Emphasis here for my purposes is
recommend policies that ensure culture
appropriate practices. Um, okay. And
number four, recommend qualifications
and processes for determination for
eligibility of financial assistance
through the patient equity fund. So
that's where we're at right now today is
at number four. um the starting point um
when it comes to indigenous and Hispanic
communities etc. the the more culturally
grounded um efforts. um we will I don't
want to say that those are not important
but we'll get of get to them as we move
along in the sense that my understanding
is a lot of it is education and
awareness um not only on the part of the
people recommending but realizing that
you know even when we're looking at
trying to provide a space for indigenous
people that we have our own prejudice of
what indigenous looks like and my big
thing is you know as a city Indian, you
know, that in itself is like a prejudice
of, you know, well, did you grow up on a
reservation? Oh, you didn't grow up on a
reservation, so does that really make
you a native person? All this other
stuff. So you know that awareness and
education but providing agency towards
the the federal federally recognized
sovereign um
uh
tribes uh nations that um they are able
to for their own people as they see fit
um provide and utilize whatever
recommendations however policies and
regulations that we have for the state
of New Mexico. we are including you in
that. Um, and that's that's how I see
that. Okay. Um, let's move on to the
presentation. Um, Denali, are you ready?
Jorge, are you ready for that? And then
we can go ahead and do some more
questions and figuring out um, how to
move along because like I said, you
know, we started off last week. We're
going to jump ahead into this
presentation. We are looking at
baselines, poverty levels, 200%, 600%
maximum. Um, and this, just so you know,
this this um presentation will not be
available right away because it's the
government and everything has to be
checked and double checked and
rechecked. And also, we have um
accessibility needs. So, it has to be in
the correct font. So, and and so so
forth. So, you won't see this right
away. um just for anyone who's dying to
get their hands on this. Okay.
>> And Despa um this is Denali. Myself and
Hanifeha are on and ready to roll.
>> Great. All right. Thank you so much for
taking the time to put this together and
presenting and you can take it away.
>> Great. Well, we um just really want to
be of Let me introduce myself first and
then ask Kifa to do that do the same.
But my name is Denali Wilson. I'm a um a
lawyer and a policy advocate. I'm also
the director of strategic support at the
Healing Advocacy Fund, which is a
nonprofit that supports state regulated
access um and with a focus on equity,
affordability.
Um and we really wanted to um partner
with others in order to make some
offerings to the this committee to
consider. And so we've partnered with
the Psychedelic Mental Health Access
Alliance. Honey will introduce herself
in just a minute and Rudik Law Group um
to just put together some considerations
for this committee.
And yeah, I'll pass it to Heneifea.
>> Thank you. Can you hear me? Okay.
>> Yeah. And and also I was gonna say if
you guys Yeah. And Hen's got it. If you
guys want to turn on your cameras while
you're presenting, you're welcome to,
but no pressure.
>> Cool. Awesome. Uh, good afternoon, good
evening, good morning, good now,
wherever you may be. My name is Hanife
Washington and I, um, am a very new
resident to New Mexico in Santa Fe. um
and I am the co-director of the
psychedelic mental health access
alliance really making to making uh it
possible for um the data and the body of
evidence to exist to support policy
makers, state policy makers, Medicaid
directors and Medicaid policy direct um
uh decision makers to have the evidence
they need to support models of care that
work within those systems so more people
can get access to these types of um
interventions when they become legal.
um when they become incorporated into
state regulated models. Um so we want to
make sure that not only are we talking
about approval, but we're talking about
access. U making sure that the the
training um and the the providers giving
the care, you know, are equipped. um
ensuring that the the care model right
is taking into consideration all types
of cultural aspects as well as
affordability um and other aspects um
that can reduce care and reduce um you
know increase barriers to this type of
care. So looking at things that impact
uh impact access and things like social
determinance of health etc. Um, and
we're really excited to be working in
New Mexico running our first pilot um,
in coordination with the University of
New Mexico and Dr. Larry Leman running a
group model care care model for PTSD
with with whole mushrooms. Um, and so we
hope to be doing studies across the
country that will follow what we're
doing here in New Mexico and again that
will build this body of evidence to, you
know, create policy change on a national
level for psychedelic assisted therapy.
Dal.
>> Yeah. Um, thanks Hanifeha and really
grateful to have been able to spend some
time on um on this project with you in
addition to all the other um incredible
work we're getting to do together.
So, uh, Desba mentioned that the
committee has had some really productive
conversations around income parameters
and so we're we're grateful to, um,
hopefully be able to supplement that
with some additional considerations.
Um, and so if you want to move to the
next slide, Jorge.
Um, we
want to, uh, offer a a number of
recommendations. some things have that
have come up in committee discussions
and and some that maybe have not yet and
and hopefully have the opportunity to to
converse about those.
Um jointly we well we we want to talk
about the the model that the state can
adopt um you know there's a community
empowerment model and a provider
empowerment model. We'll get to what
those look like in in just a moment. And
then also
um funding range considerations. I think
the the committee has already had
conversations about you know as as Desba
was saying when we opened you know the
opportunity to maybe provide treatment
to um a small group of people if we're
covering the whole care model or you
know a bigger group of folks depending
on what the parameter is. We um we put
not on income eligibility but what is
covered by the fund. Um we know that uh
cost varies with indication and we know
that it varies with different care
models. So we want to spend some time
and and ask some some questions for us
to consider as uh as we're making
recommendations for the design of the
fund. Um and then other broader
considerations around equitable access
and um sustaining the fund long term.
You can advance to the next slide.
jointly uh between PMHA, Half um Rudict
Law Group, we have some broad
recommendations. Um first, you know,
this is really premised on the
recognition that we need information
that we don't yet have in order to get
this right. you know, things like true
cost um of the the treatment and true
need measurements. Those are things that
will come with the life of the program.
And so the best thing that we can do and
I think the most responsible thing is um
you know to the best of our ability
shape uh the parameters but build in the
opportunity to adjust as information
becomes available. And so, um, to that
end, you know, we're really going to
recommend flexibility and and breadth of
eligibility to start with, um, and then
developing, um, developing the
opportunity to to refine those, uh,
those eligibility criteria as we become
more aware of the actual cost and actual
need. And then also um you know really
focusing on what the plan is to sustain
the fund over time and have some recom
some broad recommendations when we get
to that point.
Um you can advance to the next slide.
There are two primarily fund primary
fund models that I think we've talked
about in the abstract in in this um in
this committee and I think they're we're
arriving towards a consensus around what
one makes sense. Uh the first is the
community empowerment model and the next
is the the provider empowerment model
and you can advance to the next slide.
the community empowerment model. This is
like the patient applicant model um that
some states that have similar
um equity fund um analoges within either
psychedelic or other state funded
treatment programs um where where the
patient applies individually for a cash
grant um to pay for the administration
day or you know related um uncovered
treatment costs. uh such as ceremonial
healing, acupuncture, transportation to
um integration therapy. We talked about
child care as the other um another you
know uh auxiliary cost. Um and then the
provider applies for an administration
day slot at a set reimbursement rate. um
kind of similar to um the pre-approval
um of treatment in traditional um
insurance in so much as that the
reimbursement rate is set and not um not
negotiated. So that seems to be one
option that we've considered um and the
the pros and cons that have come up in
discussion in this committee. Um,
I'll start with the cons. The things
that we've heard and and talked about in
this committee is that, you know, really
we want to as much as possible relieve
the patient of the burden um of uh of,
you know, navigating the the the
bureaucracy of um applying for and then
waiting to be dispensed the funds. And
then a New Mexico specific consideration
is just the the funding infrastructure
um and vendor structure of the
department. And so um it's it's a little
more complicated for individual people
to receive funding from the department
as it is, you know, for for um a
provider in a healthcare entity.
um one consideration and this makes more
sense in in um connection with the
alternative model but is just uh it may
be that this is a little easier to
ensure compliance because they're
individual grants. Um but I I think that
that um may be navigable in in the next
model if you want to go to the next
slide.
So this is a the provider empowerment
model where a provider applies for a
lump sum um applies for and receives
lump uh funding directly from the
department in order to provide care to
eligible patients or communities. And um
it's not just something that uh you know
is a model to be considered in um the
psychedelic space but also um you know
is really common for things like vaccine
clinics. Um our bonenorphine and
methadone clinics often operate in this
model. So the department designs the the
target population which is where uh you
know the advisory board and making
recommendations about the eligibility.
Those are the parameters and then the
funding is provided directly to to
providers. And so on that um issue of uh
who holds the burden of navigating the
process, I think the major pro that
we've talked about in this committee is
uh that the provider rather than the
patient holds um the application and the
department uh you know administrative
burden. Um and and that's uh you know
something that they're set up to do that
they already regularly do if they're
receiving grants for other services or
um you know if they're engaged in in
billing Medicaid or other thirdparty
payers. Um you know they have those
structures and as I mentioned earlier
you know there is a a slightly higher
fraud risk with this model. Um but we
think that uh you know making
recommendations for um records
requirements those uh you know that are
sufficient to um protect against
fraudulent use but um you know don't
unduly threaten patient privacy. I think
that those are navigable challenges. So
um it's my sense from the the committee
and from the department that the
preference and conversation has been
around this second model. Um but perhaps
once we get through we can revive that
for conversation.
You can advance to the next slide.
So, um the the next kind of factor for
considering um and for shaping the way
that this is designed is just the
funding range. Um and you know, we're
offering these as best guess cost
estimates. As I mentioned, the committee
and the department will be in a better
position to refine um these projections
once uh you know the program is is alive
and and there will be data about how
much um administration day and full full
care protocol costs. But these are
estimates that are based on individual
treatment, so not group models um and
based on on what Colorado is is seeing
um and what's publicly available.
you can advance to the next slide.
So, these funding considerations, I
think there there are a couple of things
um to keep in mind when we're looking at
these um measures. The first is, you
know, insured and uninsured costs. Of
course, I think we've we've talked in
this committee about the desire to not
just have a fund that um that is
designed to um or not only have a fund
that is designed to cover the gap in um
people who may otherwise be insured and
eligible for coverage either through
Medicaid or another third party payer.
you know, there's a there's a part of
the care model, the administration day,
that won't ever be able to be covered by
by those um entities.
And um it's an important part that the
fund be designed to cover that. And
there are number of New Mexicans who are
are uninsured. Um and so we want to be
sure that um those who who meet the
other income requirements that they're
not um they're not uh excluded from a
fund that is designed around just this
gap. Um
an additional consideration on this
piece is that the
if we are anticipating coverage in both
um scenarios for someone who is insured
um and may have other comp other parts
of their care um protocol paid by
Medicaid or other thirdparty payers um
and people who are uninsured and in
which case the equity fund would
anticipating covering covering things
that would otherwise be covered by third
party payers, we want to be sure to not
use language that insinuates a first
party responsibility for payers. Um, so
the fund um shouldn't pay for services
for which a third party payer is liable
without first requiring a denial of
coverage or some other record in the
case of someone um, you know, who's
uninsured. Um, and then eligibility
language really should focus on
financial um, need after available
coverage and not um, financial need more
in the abstract.
Um, I think that's all on this insurance
issue, but it's a sticky one and I think
it might be easier for us to return to
once we have regulatory language. Uh but
we know on a a separate issue, you know,
that different indications really carry
different costs. And so multiple um we
we know that for certain people and
particularly for certain indications,
multiple administration days are are are
going to be necessary. And so want to
encourage the the committee to consider
alternative ways to limit um to limit
fund eligibility not just uh around you
know um not to jump to a you know this
pays for one administration day per
protocol um but rather to consider
alternative limits. So there may be a
way to craft, you know, can someone be
eligible for um a certain finite amount
of time, say 6 months, um or to cap the
total amount, you know, that that you're
eligible for up to x amount based on the
eligibility criteria. And um and that
and yeah, anything in in excess of that
amount if it's incurred because of
multiple treatment days, you know, would
be the responsibility of of the patient
or another philanthropic um potentially
philanthropic organization um to to
cover that cost.
And and we know that different care
models um carry different costs and that
the group model for example um you know
the the data that's being developed with
the UNM pilot around group care um that
part of that will will um reveal uh cost
projections for for group models um and
right at the same time that that group
is not right for every person. It's not
right for every indication. Um, and so
how can we how can we build a program uh
that provides access to funding for um
for a a multitude of different care
modalities
and ready for the next slide?
>> I think Kenneifa you wanted to take this
piece of the conversation.
>> Yes. Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Okay, cool. Thanks Denali. And just to
just to touch a little bit more on the
group model um the study um that Dr.
Larry Leman and his team and PMHA
Alliance is an implementation partner on
um we're working with um the uh Berkeley
collaboration on the economics of
psychedelics. Um and so they're going to
be helping to support a cost modeling
piece of the study uh that really looks
at the care model um and the providers
of care within that model. Um just to
give a a general synopsis. So the study
has six different groups that will move
through a 15week protocol. Um and there
are three patient groups, right? So,
veterans and first responders, women
survivors of sexual trauma, and tribal
and indigenous community members. Um,
and so each of those patient groups has
12 people. And then those groups of 12
are broken into two cohorts of six. And
so those cohorts of six move together
through the 15week protocol, which
includes the preparation sessions, two
medicine sessions, and integration
sessions. Um, and so that model, the
care model we're looking at involves two
licensed therapists and two certified
and trained peer navigators or peer
facilitators. And that means individuals
who share the identity of the people in
that patient group. So they're veterans
or their women or or first responders,
their women survivors of sexual trauma,
their indigenous or tribal folks. Again,
the overarching condition we're looking
at is PTSD. Um and the study yes is
looking at the efficacy of psilocybin on
PHTSD as much as it's looking at the
care model and its effectiveness. Um so
really testing what does it look like to
include licensed um medical providers as
well as certified facilitators that
share that peer identity. Um so those
numbers will be coming out of the study
and the first group begins its care um
starting um in June u beginning the
preparation and first medicine in July.
So just some other things to consider as
we're thinking about these these things
we've been going through and thank you
again for having us uh present today. Um
so kind of baking in questions around
equit equitable access and equity um
equity providers. Um so when as people
are applying for their license license
or certificates and their renewal we can
be asking questions do can be asking
questions at that entry point if people
will be providing this type of care. So
we create a directory so we understand
you know who are the providers and um
what types of populations with within
the fund they might be focusing on. So
it's just a a really good way to kind of
you know two birds um uh kind of one one
one feather if you will. I don't want to
say stone um but but at that entry point
getting that information at one point I
think even at the last meeting we talked
about then we could be able to create
this directory right so people will have
access to see who are all the people who
are providing um the the support through
the equity fund for for these services
and having that directory be easy to to
to access. Um and then also thinking
about something to consider again uh
kind of big vision is thinking about
okay what's this assession plan so
people um providers right uh whether
whether it's the first model or the
second model that Abdali shared what if
they move right what if they you know
transition on um what if they retire so
what happens to the funds that maybe
they have secured for those patients how
is how are those funds accounted for and
then how are they transferred to someone
else or moved back in back into the
fund. So, those are some things to
consider. Uh, another bigger question
that kind of kind of steps out a little
broader is when we when we talk about
the communities here in New Mexico and
such a rich and diverse um tribal and
indigenous indigenous communities, we
really have to understand that the
majority of these communities um do not
have this deep ancestral relationship
with psilocybin. um many of these
communities have deep ancestral
relationships with other medicines and
also ways of being in healing. So
there's a lot of education and trust
building that needs to happen as a part
of making this accessible right to these
communities. So I really want to lift up
um Dominic to you all about thinking
about if it's not the equity fund, what
funds are going to be available for the
education of these communities so that
they can come to know, understand and
trust, right? um these practices and the
offering. Um so those are the things we
want to lift up here. Thank you. Back to
you, Nolly.
Great. We have just a couple more um
slides, but I'm wondering if the hand
that's up is um something that we can
address now or should
>> Yeah, sure.
>> It is totally up to you.
>> Let's do it.
>> Would you would you like Cool. Okay.
Sounds good. So Jeff, um I am allowing
your mic and you can unmute when you're
ready.
>> Hey guys, it's State Senator Jeff
Steinborn. Um great to be with you. This
is a fantastic presentation.
Uh so thank you very much. I just have
one question. Um Denali I sorry and I
you know I didn't realize the
presentation was still going on. Um I
just for clarification when you talked
about the two different buckets or kind
of how you saw funding being available
to people the criteria you talked about
one of them was if I heard you right
that it was to cover gaps in people's
insurance coverage and since nobody's
insurance will pay for this what I
didn't hear is is that also gonna be
based upon their income or would it be
for anybody
that just didn't have insurance coverage
irrespective of income.
>> Yeah, it's a good question. Um, and I
hope you stay on uh for for a minute
longer too because we're going to get to
sustaining the equity fund and would
love to hear your perspectives about
strategy there um for insurance.
So, a part of our partnership with PMHA
has been um being in direct conversation
with the state Medicaid office and I it
was really great and um thoughtfulness
on the part of sponsors to include them
in that in the uh advisory board so that
they're at the table. And um while
you're correct that um the actual
psilocybin medicine itself and any
associated treatment for that day of the
of the care protocol will not be covered
by insurance. Um our expectation is that
Medicaid and and Medicaid has
represented that this this is their plan
as well will cover this the auxiliary um
parts of care which which we know to be
one um immense right the the preparation
work that people do often involves at
least two sessions um same with
integration um and and those are
services that Medicaid and other
thirdparty payers are already covering
in and we're so lucky to in a state
where people are already receiving
individual behavioral health services at
no cost to themselves, right? We have
legislation that requires um that people
who are are providing that insurers who
are providing that provide that at at no
co-pay to to patients. Um and so we the
parts of this care model um that don't
involve touching a schedule one federal
substance
um are uh will our expectation that is
that those will um be things that uh
providers can bill insurance for. Um so
when I talked about a gap that was the
gap does that oh go ahead
>> denalia just to say yes and thank you
senator the other thing just to like
visualize it's like actually twothirds
of the care model are those are those
conditions and um sessions that was just
saying so all the preparation sessions
and all the sessions that happen
afterward the integration sessions are
the majority of the care model right so
the the the smaller part of the care
model is actually the day of
administration depending on how many
sessions you're doing and any of the
care that's received that day. I hope
that makes it more clear.
>> It does partially and that's that was is
kind of a that was really helpful and
that's a really good point and that's
great that you guys are working on that
part of it. But I guess like if you know
for the part that isn't covered the
integration the therapy but the session
day itself
versus there may be people who have the
ability to self-pay for that session who
aren't who aren't really limited on
income and that's where I think the
equity fund is really set up to have
that income kind of through lined
because otherwise we're going to go
through the money very quickly and
>> so that's where I was just looking for a
little clar verification and uh you know
granted there's always possibility of
raising more money and all of that but
there's also a possibility that
depending upon what happens federally
even with the state that they may or may
not be agree with us on our on having
Medicaid pay for these sessions um
Medicaid pay for these um integration
sessions so I think there's a lot of
question marks but income whether it's a
small piece of it or a bigger piece of
it the income part of
I still think is an important
consideration, but um but I'll just kind
of leave it at that and I know it's an
ongoing process here and I really
appreciate the effort you're putting
into this and you as well. Thank you all
and Madam Chair, thank you to you too.
Thank you guys.
>> Yeah, thanks Senator and sorry that I
didn't emphasize um the income.
Oh, shoot. I think let's see. It looks
like we lost Denali.
Um, we don't have Yeah, we're not
getting any audio.
Um,
>> hey Denali, we can't hear you.
>> Okay. Yeah, and it's showing showing
your mic trying to do something, but
yeah, we're not getting anything. Um,
yes. So, Denali possibly if you want if
you can hear us if you might want to hop
off and hop back on again. That'll
probably fix it.
>> Lea, she doesn't uh not able to get back
on. Do you want to continue with the
last two slides? Because there's slides
10 and 11.
>> Hold on a second. She's texting me.
Okay, let's just pause for a second.
Um,
says I'm
kicked out or kicked out.
Okay. Says that it's kicked her out.
Can you log back in?
Let's see. Since it's show still showing
her in the meeting, I'm going to try
removing her from the meeting now and
then I'll resend.
>> Okay,
>> I can try resending her the link.
>> Okay, I'll let her know.
>> Hey, they're going to completely log you
out of the meeting and resend you the
link. Period.
Um, since we have this little pause, um,
if Senator Steinborn is still on, I just
kind of wanted to clarify a little the
last part that, um, you mentioned about,
>> um, I I totally understand the question
in the sense of like if we have,
>> um, if a person is a patient is
available to pay for portions of their
treatment. So that there's let's say
that there's five steps and they're able
to pay for four of the five steps but
the only part of the step they're not
able to pay which is itself the
psilocybin treatment day. Um then what I
hear you saying is then we kind of
we want to focus more on being able to
provide the equity fund to the people
who may not be able to pay for anything
at all is what I kind of heard you say
and I just wanted to have clarification
on that.
Yeah, I I think that's correct, Esba.
But, you know, that's that's kind of I
think the the belief in which the equity
fund was launched is to provide
treatment for people who literally don't
have the financial means to cover it
themselves or, you know, not reasonably
afford to be able to do it. So, but it
sounds like there's kind of an expanded
school of thought maybe being proposed
and I'm not I'm not invalidating that,
but it's just flagging it a little bit.
>> Totally appreciate it. No, and I and I
thank you for that for that
clarification. And um while we get um
just let me know when Denali gets back
on board or
>> Okay.
>> Hi. Sorry.
>> Yeah, that's okay. That's okay. We we
will definitely we value that opinion.
We value like I want to say all opinions
um because this is this is the struggle
and the challenge of trying to figure
out what to do um in the sense of you
know there are metrics that we need to
to to hit and also we are trying to care
for the community and it's not easy to
try to like think for everybody. Um, you
know, think of this as like the
household. You know, you have a person
trying to figure out like what's the
best use of, you know, 10 pounds of meat
and like a gallon of milk and like what
are you going to make for dinner? It's
really just kind of figuring out what
we're trying to do and and you know,
you're not going to give the smallest
one equal portions of a growing
teenager. You know, it's just I know
that's a really bad analogy, but we're
all these opinions and all these ideas
of how we should be able to use it is is
good. And I think that being able to
kind of come up with the framework,
plugging in the different variables and
understanding like the mission of what
we're trying to do is really important.
So, with that, I'll get back to Denali
and Hanipa.
>> Yeah, thanks. Sorry if I don't know what
happened, but I'm back. Um, and I think
maybe this is a good opportunity for me
to I missed the last meeting, but my
understanding in the recap and from the
the notes was that the committee is um
considering a range from 200
um% of the federal poverty line to 600
and that there will be like a sliding
scale. So someone who is at the lower
end of that range would have full um
coverage for whether it's the
administration day or full care um in
line with the spirit that I'm hearing
senator remind us of. And then you know
as their income increases the the
coverage from the equity fund decreases
until someone has an income at which
they're excluded from eligibility.
I think that was what I understood the
the current um considerations to be.
>> Yeah. And and then just before you start
again and then just to kind of put a pin
in that you know it could be that and
and this is where like I was saying like
the mathematicians and everybody who
works with this you know more often than
I do is you know it could be that we
have a number of applicants that you
know completely depleted at you know the
200% poverty level uh where we provide
full 100% coverage for that treatment
and then you know the other uh sliding
scale applicants that may be like, hey,
you know, we could possibly afford 50%.
You know, they they they just don't this
round, this round are not um going to,
you know, get their coverage treat uh
provided at 50%, because we maxed out at
100. So, that's where like all of this
uh sliding around figuring out the
parameters, you know, what where where
and where and where and where and where
and where and where and when we're going
to max out and how um I think is really
important conversation. So, continue
Great. I think we're ready for the next
slide.
And I just have there's only two more.
>> Yeah, this is it. Number uh 10. Yep.
Right there.
Correct.
>> Oh, perfect. Um
so uh the the additional considerations
a couple that we wanted to um flag for
the committee for consideration
um is can for the department to consider
including equity pro fund provider
questions right the whether someone if
if we're going the the provider
empowerment route where providers
receive funding
>> um that if that's the f if that's the
route that we go um that they include
those those uh questions in um
>> I think we already
>> the application and renewal. Oh, go
ahead.
>> We already did this slide.
>> We already did.
>> Did we talk about the equity fund?
>> No, this this is 10 and 11 are still
still the two that Okay, this is slide
10 and these are the last two. It's all
right.
>> Okay. Thought we did this. I think I
think Denali is frozen again.
>> No.
Okay.
Um
and
>> well uh while that is happening uh this
is Dominic and I'll just go ahead and
jump in is that we've already talked
about uh as far as um the providers
needing to answer a few questions. And
one thing to remind everybody if you
haven't been to some of the other
meetings, but we've talked about this in
others, is that we will have a list of
the providers available on the DO
website because since the providers have
to all be permitted, we will have that
list there and available. And so within
that, one of the things that we can do
is put an indication there uh that says
whether or not they accept the equity
funds and or if they offer other um
discounts or sliding scale fees or other
similar things so that patients have an
idea uh when they're moving into that
area and into that realm. So um this is
a great consideration and it's one that
we've already discussed a little bit but
not a whole lot but definitely one that
does need to be included in. So, uh,
really great to hear it and see it from
other people presenting it. Oh, and it
looks like Denali is coming back on in.
So, hopefully that will have been
good timing on that.
>> Sorry. Hopefully that's the last time
that happens.
>> Oh, you're good. I would also probably
just suggest turning off your video.
That might be one of the things that's
causing it. So,
>> yeah.
Okay. So, I was maybe repeating
something that we already covered. Is
that right?
>> Yeah.
>> What I was just saying though, Denali,
is that uh the ideas on this slide are
definitely things that the department
has already talked about and it's been
talked about some of the other
committees listing the providers and
actually putting something there if they
offer discounts or if they are
accepting, you know, uh equity fund etc.
And so, yeah, no disagreements on this.
Okay, great. Glad to be on the same
page. So, um on the last slide,
sustaining the equity fund.
Um
so we have
uh $630,000
that was given through um growth funding
uh which is not an ordinary mechanism by
which state agencies received funding
for things like this. But we were really
grateful to have the creativity and
leadership of individual lawmakers who
wanted to be sure that the fund was um
the funding of the fund was accelerated
on this accelerated timeline um despite
not being in the executive or LFC budget
um you know really jumped too. So um the
reality is so normally growth funds have
to be used in two years but because the
funds were given to a non-reverting fund
in the statute they can be used at any
time. Um that being said, I think based
on the um parameters that have been
discussed, there should be um no
difficulty in making these funds
available uh to to patients within the
the timeline of the program.
Um
the there is you know broadly just a
political consideration that I think um
we should talk about as talking of as
you know relevant to the parameters that
are designed. Um really the question for
the legislature will be how far was the
department able to make this initial
investment go. And I think um you know
as as much as we want to make the funds
available um to as many folks as
possible um and provide that breath, I
do think um there is an important
political consideration of how um how
how far the the department is able to
how many people how many patients um and
individuals the department is able to
reach with the funds.
um that maybe lends to a little more
conservative of parameters. Um and that
that's really important because I think
this is going to set the stage of how
the legislature responds to future asks.
Uh I think the expectation is that it
will be um incorporated into the
department of health's um annual budget
at some reasonable measure. Um and uh
being able to demonstrate in the first
you know one two years of the program um
the the the
um
the breadth um of the the the impact of
the fund is is going to be really um
really key.
So um there will be an opportunity I
think that has to happen for the
legislature and reporting that's um
that's going to be the burden of the
department to to share with the
legislature how the funds have been used
but also really valuable to the the
subcommittee itself um and refining the
eligibility that's designed um in order
to uh maximize the impact of the fund in
the future. Um but incremental fund use
analysis is is uh something that um will
be necessary to sustain the fund to
demonstrate to the legislature the the
effectiveness
um and and ultimately to um to s yeah
yeah sustain the fund in the long term.
Um, one I don't know where these live
normally. Maybe the senator maybe the
senator does. But I found you know there
there is going to be a requirement that
the um department provide to uh the
legislature about how the funds are
used. It's like a progress bar um for
growth funds. I'm sharing one that was
from the council and um I forget what
this entity is but often is holding
growth funds for for different state
agencies. Um but right the what the
legislature wants to know you'll see
this outcome bar um how many people were
impacted and and I that goes to the
political calculus that I think is
important for us to to keep in mind when
we're thinking about the long-term
sustainability.
Um so there's really you know I think
two um distinct responsibilities the the
department um you know will incorporate
the sustaining of the equity fund uh
into future annual budgets um as is
possible within their other budget
constraints. And then the community has
an ongoing role um to to to
um
uh sustain legislative support. And I
want to just remind folks of how much
community input um and uh and
encouragement was necessary to uh get
the investment that we had. you know,
there was a community letter that had
about 30 different behavioral health
organizations and psychedelic
organizations
um that went out to people who were in
decision-m
um roles about the need for the equity
fund and and that's something that we'll
we'll need to continue to do.
And that's all I have. Ana, you have
anything else to add? Um just one thing
and thank you so much Jali and I believe
that this was covered Dominic you
mentioned at the last meeting that
perhaps going forward with this one this
is a type of fund that is also can
receive funds from outside like so from
philanthropic support and things of this
nature. So it seems like perhaps that
that will be also a way where community
can support the sustaining of of this of
this fund. Thank you.
>> Yes, that is correct. Thank you.
That's all for today. Thank you so much
for giving us this time today.
>> Thank you so much for providing all of
this information. I do see that there
are some comments in the chat and I did
kind of want to um put some highlights
and some notes into uh the presentation
um from my perspective
um to you know potentially look at in
the future. the one on the slide on the
community empowerment um for the I feel
like you know this could possibly be uh
an instance where this might be for the
border towns and the PBLO or for
individual members who may be living on
tribal land where their tribes may or
may not be providing. they decided that
they don't want to have, you know, this
particular um program on their, you
know, for, you know, as as a whole for
their citizens. um that maybe that might
be an instance where you know a border
town whether it's um Bernal Leo County
for Santa Ana and so forth or Los Luna's
area um Bolen you know or Farmington
Gallup in those places that you know we
have these particular um individuals who
are on tribal land and I don't know
again this is this is just the first
thought that came to my mind when I saw
that slide um
uh and then also for the slide Um
there's a I had a question on the
ensuring the eligibility is not limited
to one administration session. Um
for those of us who are newly attending
these meetings, just so you know, we are
working on coming up with uh definitions
that are used across the committees and
we're not I don't think we're quite just
there yet. So maybe things might be a
little bit different. Um so just from my
personal understanding can can we um
define this idea in your u presentation
about the administration session?
>> Yes. Um so it would be a so like we were
sharing before we have these different
conditions under the bill right so for
example PTSD
um the the protocol the clinical
protocol that's needed will probably not
just be one session or one
administration of receiving the the
medicine you might need two or three
sessions. So will the equity fund will
there be a limit right on the number of
sessions administrative sessions of
receiving the molecules um and being in
the in the medical protocol that will be
set. Will it be per session or will it
be about the whole clinical protocol? So
say there's like a whatever it's a six
weeks protocol or a 14week protocol. Is
it going to cover that whole time or is
it only going to just cover one of the
three sessions that are needed for that
treatment? Does that make more sense?
>> Yeah. And so I'm just I'm trying to make
sure I understand the presentation
because in my mind when I'm thinking
Yeah. There's different there's
different sessions and we're labeling as
the intake and then we're labeling them
as the journey or the treat the actual
treatment session like
>> administration. Yeah. Go ahead. Sorry.
>> Yeah. And then there's the integration
session. So in my mind, I'm always
compartmentalizing them into like
essentially like three sessions.
>> Um, and so that's why I was trying to
make sure that I clarified
administration sessions. So
administration session, you're saying
all of the sessions are falling under
administration.
>> No, no. Administration would be the
receiving of the molecule. So the the
medical
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. When you're administering the
medicine. Yeah.
>> The actual treatment itself with Okay.
when you're actually intake um taking in
psilocybin.
>> Yeah. Intake, medicine, and
administration are kind of like
synonymous.
>> Yeah,
>> I know. In my mind, it's not. I'm like
intake is like you're talking to someone
through teaalth.
>> Sure.
>> To me, treatment is like I'm actually
sitting taking psilocybin into my my
being. And to me, integration is like
I'm back to talking to someone through
possibly tellaalth. And to me in my mind
it's completely
>> that's why I was asking for the
clarification. Okay.
>> Gotcha. Yes.
>> And um let's see. Equitable I had this
note here. Equitable access
considerations funds access for
providers. I only think I had this note
down just to kind of make sure again for
everyone. Um you know we are looking at
the different sides. We're also looking
at um for providers we're looking at uh
propagation which is a completely
different committee but in this
particular um
uh
when we're looking at access for the
providers
I feel like that's
um I might need another clarification on
that one in that particular slide. I
wish I had written down which slides
they were, but
um then I had group model versus that.
Gosh, I can't remember what that Sorry,
my I didn't write down really good
notes. Um
>> that's what I can pull up the slides if
you if you tell me what it said. I can
pull that one up. Let me know.
>> It said access considerations fund
access for providers. I think it was
some had something to do with Hanifo
talking about the group models. Okay.
>> I Okay. Yeah, I found it. Give me one
second.
>> There it is.
>> Let's see. Okay.
All right. Administration day primary
pay. Okay. Void language and the first
I'm going to have to look at this slide
just a little bit more so I can wrap my
head around it better. But I think
Oh, okay. This is going to be a little
hard for me to try to clarify what I was
thinking about.
When we're looking at the different
areas demographically and or
geographically throughout the state.
This was my understanding and this is
where I need a little clarification. I
just for some reason something popped
into my head about
again kind of similar to tribal lands
and sovereign nations maybe not wanting
to have this particular medicine. Um
that if we were to have say an
overabundance
of providers and or funds for that
particular place.
What then would be the
what what would happen then? I don't
know that that maybe that's getting too
far ahead, but something about this
slide made me think of that and I don't
know if there was a correlation to that
slide where you know we do you know
maybe maybe the maybe the numbers are
saying I keep throwing espanola out
there because that's where I'm from but
you know maybe the numbers are saying
that the number of people who may or may
not have this um and you're providing it
but no one's actually utilizing it Um,
and I think that's why I had a question
about fund access for providers and
equitable access considerations.
Um, then do we pull back? Are we still
just kind of allowing the funds or how
that works? And maybe that's just a
completely off-the-wall question that
has no basis in this particular slide,
but that was just something that just
kind of came to mind and I don't know if
it even makes sense to have that
question. Um, and I just want to also
point out that um, we did get
clarification on the gap insurance
coverage. Um, and then we did get a
little bit I wanted to also put a pin in
the idea of funds for education kind of
on that same wavelength, right? I know
we want to hit as many people in the in
the areas or the people who may who need
it the most. Um but again like say for
instance if we are looking at what would
drive the need for more funding or um
availability for funds for people if
we're going through provider-based I
think that's what it was provider-based
eligible eligible funds in an area that
we think is hardest hit who may use them
the most but no one's actually taking
advantage of them. Um then what happens?
Would we then kind of siphon that money
back into the funds and or would be able
to then allocate that money for
education so at least that there's
awareness and kind of going back to this
idea of agency for that for that
community to even though um the funding
is provided to the providers but no
one's actually taking on um there's no
patients. I doubt that that's the case,
but um then would we be able to use that
money for education awareness? I think
that's where I was going with that
question. And
okay, and then just back to the last to
the last slide. Um
you know I think that perhaps maybe one
of our target points is to work with the
research committee andor just you know
using the models and the grow uh scale
that uh Denali used you know when we are
able to have that framework for the data
that we're getting from how well we were
able to allocate the funds through the
um equity fund um you know it may not be
able to be that the next legislation
session they were getting repeated
recreated funds for the for of this
particular equity fund. Um because I
think that was something that uh Senator
Seinborn if he's still on uh mentioned
in the previous uh meeting was
it's a matter of kind of hitting
different p different aspects of this um
situation um from different angles. So
right now we're providing the equity
fund for the patients themselves either
through providers or through maybe these
grants um through the community empower
uh model
but it might also be that we need to
find a way to fund for providers. how we
might need to fund for propagation and
in that case we're trying to make sure
that we are providing support in all
aspects of the medical psilocybin
treatment and not just for patients but
it might also be facilitators it might
also be for propagation I'm not sure um
but I still think it's important to
understand
all of the data that we are getting from
this how well this model and this
framework worked and what didn't work um
so that we can provide that information
for the future for you know for the next
maybe not this legislative session but
for you know for for sessions to come
and or just in general because the more
we are educated and aware of like the
problems and the challenges that we're
having just like Oregon and Colorado
then we can actually figure out a
possible way to like move forward ahead
and as um Siobhan said earlier maybe
this might be models for other things in
the future. Okay. Anyone else who has
questions and or comments, please um
let's let's uh Does anyone Greg while I
read through and see who's here? Greg,
do you want to go ahead and chime in?
>> Um is Denali and Hanifea still here?
>> Hey, we're on.
>> Yes, I'm still here. Hey, back on slide
number eight, the one that we were just
looking at. Um,
while um I have a question about the
dollars, um, and while you're pulling
that up, if you could, um, regarding the
paying growers, um, Desba, I think we've
thought about this and I think there's
not a logical path for federal or or for
maybe for state funds cuz that's right,
they are state funds. I just don't think
that like paying the the pro producers
is an easy path. Um,
let that sit. Um, question for the
um lawyer and program directors in the
room. Um, have we uh have do we have a
detailed breakdown of where these um
costs come from or go to or like what
dollars go to go to where? I know that
there we're dealing with fuzzy numbers,
but how detailed is this estimate?
>> Yeah. Um, that's a great question and
I'll be honest that these were just the
the fastest numbers we could come up
with based on like going through the
intake process in Colorado a number of
select Colorado clinical providers. Um,
so that's what it's based on is Colorado
clinical track. Um, got it. But I think
uh and what's not available to me now
but could become available if it's
helpful to the committee or um to others
looking at this. Um while we don't have
our own cost estimates
um you know I think that the request for
a more detailed breakdown of what the
costs are makes a lot of sense for for
us thinking.
>> No I think it was a good starting point.
>> Yeah. I think the I think one of
actually like I think a very I think we
need to hold this and I think a really
valuable metric to track as we move into
the program is can New Mexico do better
than this like if we're truly a program
designed for uh equity and access like
that through the whole ethos of the
system can we do better than this and
it's like and we have to understand that
these are costs pre-insurance so like
these are built like therapist's
billable hours, right? So, like we're
not going to, you know,
adjust those. Um, but like cost to
patient versus cost to like total cost
is something worth measuring. And then
one additional question
for I I mean guess the room, but um I
imagine Hanifeha probably has some
detailed clarity on this, but
as we go through this and we measure
efficacy and measure program success um
in telling that story back over to the
legislators who are going to go help us
find more money Um, what are the things
that we
need to see and what what are what are
the what are the goals that we need to
like the metric goals that we need to
set
um set our sights on from the beginning?
>> Greg, can you just restate that really
quickly like just concisely?
>> Absolutely. Yeah. um what are the metric
goals that we need to focus on from the
beginning to define efficacy that allow
us to I guess a bring insurance onto our
team and b get more uh legislative funds
allocated
and we might not have an answer today.
Yeah, I think that's a big question, but
immediately I would say the kind of big
buckets, right, that we need to be
looking at include
does this treatment work, right? Does it
work? Are the patient outcomes positive?
>> Oh, I'll answer that. Yes.
>> Right. Are they more positive than other
types of treatments that exist?
Is this creating a pathway to more
equitable access to mental health
coverage? Um
and the the cost analysis, right? That's
I mean the biggest thing is like
because you can have a model that is
creating great patient outcomes, but if
it's super expensive. So you want to be
looking at yeah the billable hours, the
time um licensed versus
not licensed or whether it's like
licensed medical license versus versus
certified care team composition. Um, and
but I think that this is a big question
for us to maybe this is a homework
question and we can come back to the
next meeting with some answers to this
question.
>> Yay, homework. Thank you. No, that that
helps.
>> Yeah. And I think I mean I it's all
these are great questions even even some
that are off topic. I'll just say that
you know just maybe be aware of not that
they have been but just you know if we
have off-topic you know they're good
questions. Putting it out there is
great. Um, but I think it seems perhaps
that life that's a little bit farther
down, but we should be aware of it. Um,
and just a quick numbers thing at and
tell me if I'm correct on this. So, what
we're looking at, at least according to
that slide that Greg just pulled up, the
eighth slide on the numbers where the
lower end was $3,500 for an
administration day. So, as again, this
is clarification with Hanifha about the
administration day. Um, so my math tells
me that at the lower end at $3500 per
administration day, that means that
there's 180
uh treatment
uh days, administration days.
So if a person may or may not have like
say six administration days, that's only
30 patients. Now, am I wrong in that
math?
And I'm just saying this just so we're
not freaking out at the end of here and
saying we're only looking at 30 people.
And I'm like, yes, we are only looking
at 30 people. That's why that's why
we're going through figuring out
how how well this model is going to
look. the data that's involved. And yes,
there will probably most likely be
someone who did not benefit from this in
some ways. There will probably be
somebody um because as we all know and
we accept that this is not necessarily
something that is is is that someone may
or may not find that is beneficial
regardless if it is. Um but we have to
be accepting of that um as part of if
we're truly scientists, this is the
thing that we're looking at. Um but to
that end, this is why having a detailed
account of, you know, all of where the
money went, how it was, how it was uh
the number of treatments, which ones
were successful. That's why this program
is so important so that we can look back
on it and build and learn from it for
the future and also too for other states
and other programs who might look at it
and be like yes they either got it right
or they got it wrong but we have to be
accepting of those things. Um Hanifha.
Yes.
>> Yeah. I I think this, you know, is
hearkening us back to the last meeting,
you know, where we, you know, were given
the homework, right? Like come up with
what what the caps and numbers should
be. And I think, you know, what the
senator brought up today, you know, and
what we keep reiterating, right? Like
is, you know, we're coming up with this
200 to 600. Maybe it's just like we have
to decide for reaching more people that
who are really in need to be like well
maybe it is just for people who are at
you know below the poverty and and not
like people who can afford to pay any of
it. Maybe it's only for people who can't
pay any of it um to be able to get it to
to the most people in need. So um I
think we have to really look at based on
what our homework was from last time. Do
we think that this range that we're
saying we're starting at is actually the
right place to start? Do we need to come
down on on that 600 level?
>> Uh thank you, Teneifa. Uh Siobhan,
>> can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, I've spent about $22,000
of my own money on my own journey to try
to heal myself on, you know, plant-based
medication. Um,
around 4,000 of that was spent on um
psilocybin within itself, right? And
then I kind of went through the
different lists of of things that you
can do after that because I wasn't
getting results that I wanted or you
know uh I had treatment resistant PTSD
and depression. So with that I mean
obviously the costs are going to be a
lot higher for for people for
individuals and it's it's you never
really know what the the outcome of the
treatment is. You know, even with my
Ibegan journey, I was the only person
out of 10 that needed a booster dose,
you know, and so it's really just
depends on the patient, but I I can
understand where you're you're coming up
with maybe like 30 only 30 people cuz if
these 30 people have treatment
resistant, you know, uh PTSD, they're
going to need more sessions. they're
going to need more help, more
integration and all of that to even
receive or to even see um you know
results. So yeah.
Okay. And then I just um before Denali
speaks uh and we're just so we know
we're at the 4:30 mark.
But um you bring up a good point Siobhan
and I just kind of wanted to point back
to one of the things that Denali brought
up in the slides was the gap insurance
coverage. you know that this is I'm just
saying like this is lower end 60 I
thought was like a low end but then you
know if we have six sessions that are
fully covered and when I'm saying
administration day I was thinking based
on the slide that this is the intake you
know the the therapy talk you know prior
to intake administration day and then
also like the journey treatment
administration day and then also the
integration um end of it talk therapy uh
administration day. So I was thinking
six sessions total including all of the
sessions per person. It could be the
person needs five. But if we're taking
into consideration the gap insurance
maybe this is only for the treatment
itself which is the um in taking the
psilocybin molecule. Um and I just
wanted to point that out but uh Denali
did you want to go ahead and say
something?
Yeah, I just wanted to um
share. So, I wasn't in the last meeting
in the discussion of ranges, but I it's
just my perspective that 600% of the po
poverty line is is pretty high income
for most of New Mexico. And I think um
you know to the points that the senator
made about um the uh you know what
really was the spirit of how this money
was given by individual lawmakers and I
think what I'm hearing from others um it
it may be smart to consider reducing
that range. I know that that was going
to be within a sliding scale model. Um,
but 600% of the federal poverty line in
in New Mexico is is for most even, you
know, in Albuquerque and and Santa Fe is
is is pretty high income. Um, so I just
wanted to give my perspective on that.
And then just quickly thinking about how
we
do a range. If if we are talking about a
range and sliding scale, I want to
recommend that um we be clear in
language that the start of the range is
200 if that's the number we go with 200%
or lower so that you don't inadvertently
exclude people who make less less than
200% of the federal poverty line. if
that makes sense. That shouldn't it
shouldn't start at 200, but if we're
doing the sliding scale, the 100%
coverage goes up to 200% and then
decreases at whatever the the final
threshold is.
>> Yeah. And I think that that's, you know,
that's a good uh point to make. I can't
bring up the chart that we had the last
time. I think it was actually through
the um health alliance that we used it
from. Um, and you're right. To me, my
understanding was 200 and below that
would be 100%. And then anywhere above
200% to 600 was capping out to zero. And
it could shift over more very much so.
So that it's um 150 or even 100%. 100%
poverty line, federal poverty line, and
below you get full treatment costs 100%.
Um, and then it can scale up to 300%.
Um, I can't remember why. Um, I think it
was in my notes somewhere, but I think
that was like $50,000.
Um, and that was the reason why starting
at the 200%.
Um,
but we could we it could definitely
shift down to to I was try what I was
thinking is that we were shifting it up
to 200% and below was 100% need met.
Yes. And then above that then if you
made six $60,000 then that's when the
sliding scale started. That was my
understanding. I could have completely
bosched that in my understanding and the
way we were using it. Um,
okay. Is there any other questions? I'm
gonna start kind of looking into the
chat. Um, I know that there was Jim
Dodson. I know you had some stuff to
say. Did you want to speak to what you
were talking about? Um, if it had
because I know that there was some stuff
here.
Okay.
All right.
as I can't tell if they're having a
conversation amongst yourselves um in
the chat or if you actually are having
wanting to contribute to the the
conversation in this in this particular
space. Chris,
>> hello everyone. Hello Des
um letting me come on. I'm uh just
wanted to echo what Denali was saying
and and what Jim's saying in the chat
is, you know, I think we should um use
the money to treat the people that can't
afford it at all. And there was a a
couple other comments I had in one of
the slides. You know, it kind of alluded
to group treatment may cost differently.
And I I think there's kind of a
perception that it's going to be a whole
lot cheaper. And I I don't know that
that's going to be the case from what
I've heard from a lot of people in
Colorado that, you know, when they run
groups, it doesn't really save money.
Um, and so I wanted to challenge that a
little bit. And I also wanted to talk a
little bit about how follow-on
treatments may not end up being as
expensive. you know, so if somebody
needs two or three sessions,
there's not likely to be as much
preparation
or um
yeah, work around those. So, that might
be a little a little bit of cost savings
there. Um
but those are just some thoughts I had.
I I think we should keep it to
um serve the people that that need it
the most. And 600% poverty line. I I was
just looking that up. I think that's way
too high for that population group to be
getting any help and we need to reserve
them the money for people that need it
more.
>> Thank you.
>> And yeah, thank you, Hanifha.
>> Okay. Yeah, thank you. Um yeah, I think
that depending on the condition and the
model Chris and and others like there's
a lot that we don't know about group um
particularly for these conditions which
is why I think there's going to be a lot
of like truthtelling coming out of the
study that we're running. So I
appreciate that push back and I think on
paper it can look like it's cheaper,
right? Um but when it comes to the
entire care model, right, when it's not
just the administration day, that's
where I think we see it kind of evening
out. So I think you're you're fair to
raise that. The question that I had or
the consideration was around um
was was thinking about you know ho how
do we um yeah I just seconding again
like I I think looking at 200 and below
or you know that really looking at
people who really can't afford this at
all um can should be considered first
because there's this whole thing that
happens right because what about if
awareness grows about this that this
exists and you have this sliding tunnel
in the beginning maybe some of the
people who are below the poverty line
don't know about it but then as the time
goes forward they learn about and they
want to do it but now all these funds
have been given away to folks who are at
sliding scale so I think there's just a
fundamental thing to and I would you
know second third and fourth like it
this should be for people who really
can't afford it at all you know um and
then work our considerations from from
there as opposed to opening up broader
thank you
>> and Greg Okay.
Couple things.
Um
I'm curious.
I don't know how to answer like how to
really answer, but um efficacy. I think
there's a lot of things in that make
people impoverished, right? And there's
a lot of like
effect of being impoverished.
And
there is undoubtedly a correlation
of
uh safe containers to return to which
are directly tied to. and safe
containers like a stable household, not
worrying about food every day, like not
re-entering those whatever traumas you
live on a daily basis.
Um, and those being tied to efficacy.
So,
it's funny from a research model, is it
like as a researcher, would it be wise
if I wanted to show efficacy that I
would just have rich white people go
through my study because they would all
just get better and go back to their
corporate jobs? So there may be a real
difference in care, continuity of care,
the containers that we uh create for
people. uh community programs that like
what if the fund
supported um not basketball courts, but
like you know like uh ongoing
public community meetings like uh in
what what do we call those things like
in integration sessions or like whatever
like uh when people get together and
talk about psychedelics and it's just a
community event. um those could be
highly effective for people that don't
have a community to go back to or a safe
container um after their treatment.
>> Thank you, Greg, for that. Um before
Heneife, um I just kind of wanted to
make a point. You you make a really good
point, Greg. Um
the integration and the community and
the environment. I think was it recid
reciticism
um and I know that that's not
necessarily the case in in this for
hoping you know a lot of people have you
know had one session of psilocybin and
and every you know it's it's rainbows
and puppy dogs for the rest of their
lives but you're right that's not always
the case um and it does have to do with
your environment the sentence setting
doesn't go away just after the
integration process with the medicine
that has to do with the wraparound
support that is in that community and
that is vitally important to to uh that
person being back in there because
everybody anyone could possibly know.
It's like you've been to like the most
amazing place, you've gone to the most
amazing concert, you've gone on the most
amazing hike and you come back and you
tell someone about it and it falls on
deaf ears and you don't have that
support and you don't have that
community. So what you're saying, Greg,
is is incredibly important to to take
into consideration.
I'm not sure that it would necessarily
for the program itself, but I hear and I
think that that is is vitally important
to understand that that those support
systems that we provide to a person um
afterwards um or how we can help them if
they can keep coming back or you know
like that in itself is part of the
research and or making sure that this is
a lasting impact. Um so I just kind of
want to point that out. All right. Uh,
Henifa, did you still want to say
something?
>> No, I'm complete.
>> I'm going to pass. I don't know if
you're going to hear me.
>> Pass.
Sorry, I didn't realize that I had my
mic off. I was just going to Thank you,
Heneifeha. Um, I was just going to read
I think Senator Seinborn's comment.
Because of the data collection component
built into law, in theory, our program
would capture data that could be parsed
for income and other demographic data.
Okay. Um, I just kind of wanted to throw
something out there. Did I know last
time we said the baseline would be 200%
and then we would, um, I'm thinking what
I'm hearing is kind of actually just
capping it. um at you know if you fall
200%
below poverty line do we want to reduce
that down to whatever the next level
that is to 150 or 175
um of the poverty level and below and
then just cap it there. Um that I think
that might sound like that's what
everyone is kind of looking at. Um,
and I I'm the last person to know
anything about what income levels are. I
mean, I'm living in Santa Fe and I'm
ekking out an existence and I don't know
how I'm doing it. It's by the grace of
God. I'll just tell you that much. Um,
and that's completely going to be
something different than someone else in
in a different area. Um so if anyone who
has actual um information on where we
could possibly cap it and this not above
that right so we're not actually looking
at 600% poverty level we're not looking
at 300% poverty level or you know maybe
we are but what would be the capping
point and Hanifeha
>> go ahead Hanifa
>> hi yes thank you I I I'm not a
mathematician but I would say something
in that arena and just form a point of
process. I think that we also want to um
create
um
you know space trap doors if you will to
be like and we will we would recommend
setting it at this place now and then in
six months into the process review it
and see where we're at because like if
nobody's using it right and it's just
like not it's not being used we might
want to bake in something that says and
we'll revisit this and and re-recommend
if we need to or something like that.
But I do again agree starting in that
lower uh range makes the most sense.
>> Okay. And Greg, did you want to go ahead
and comment on your comment?
>> No. Um I was just putting numbers in
there. Um I was I I want to I want to
make sure that we're continuing the
consideration of uh preference to uh
marginalized communities, however we
define that. Um whereas like economic
marginalization is one thing but then
there's historic marginalized
communities that are uh abundant in our
state. So I don't know if it gets into a
a kind of
lack of funds like how do we mar how do
we
how do we measure preference to
Yeah. I think I think that makes sense.
>> Okay. I think what I hear you saying is
yes, we need to have a marker for let's
just say put it at three uh 100%. Right?
But let's just say the first people who
hear about this are people in Santa Fe.
What about all the people that are in
the other parts of the state?
Is that kind of what I'm hearing is just
like if we have everyone applying from a
particular area and they're like, you
know, but we're forgetting about
Lordsburg, we're forgetting about um
Roswell, we're forgetting about
Espanola, we're forgetting about and and
I know that's still geographic, but like
that's what I mean by marginalized is
that I feel like to me in some ways the
more rural communities like Chimayo
>> to me is more rural. I want to say
>> geographically
>> geographically marginalized.
>> Um so we're not making sure that we do
have a component that's in there for the
Hispanic indigenous under reppresented
uh peoples in those particular places.
Definitely. I think so. I feel we have
comments going on just that they're
heading up the last little 15 12
minutes. Um
>> 12 minutes. Um, so yeah, like I think I
think putting the cap on the money is
one thing, but then like once we have
that cap on like and there's 50 people
in line and is it like women and
children first, quote unquote like I'm
not saying that specifically, but it
what's the mentality of uh preference
for equity, right? Are we trying to
define equity as I heard about this
first and I showed up? we do need to
make sure the money gets spent, but like
how do we build in those um levy markers
and variables that will inevitably come
up in conversation? But yeah, I also
fully support the review period that
Heneifeha
um Mark mentioned.
>> Okay, so there are other markers and
other metrics that people should also
perhaps meet so that we can make sure
that we do and what does that look like
and what are those markers? Okay. Um,
let's see who was going to next.
Yeah. Um,
oh shoot. Did I forget what I was going
to say? I maybe did.
Oh. Oh, no. I remembered. Okay. Sorry.
It's the end of the day, guys.
Um, I I think this is maybe another pro
for the provider empowerment model,
which is similar to like the way that
the department does vaccine clinics and
um substance use treatment clinics. that
would allow the department to say what
they they may have other tools at their
disposal to to measure around geographic
need. But I'm I'm thinking vaccines is
like a really good example of where
we've said, "Okay, this is how many
people are here who we know need like we
can measure the need and then create the
RFP or whatever to providers to um fill
that need that is related to the actual
geographic need. That might be a another
factor in the pro column for the
provider based. Um because as the the
hypothetical that you were um walking
through Desba is like people
individually applying, right? That
that's like the it's like first come
first serve um in a sense. I mean,
there's there's other ways that the
department could limit um and create uh
structure around who actually receives
funding and create prioritization, but
it might be easier um if we do adopt the
the provider empowerment model. Um to
create u as much geographic equity as
possible um
yeah under under those that model of um
of administration.
Okay, that's a good point. I'm not
familiar with the vaccine model in in
that regard. Um, so I think that's a
really good point to where you were
saying the provider provider model. Um,
we just have nine minutes left and I
kind of just wanted to put a bullet out
there. Should we cap it at um it's going
to be I'm just we have a suggestion here
of 300% 350 and those guidelines
currently are at 47,800
according to the math that uh Greg um
put out there. Um so this is just for
capping to move away from what we had
discussed last um Dominic you have a
question. Okay. Um maybe we don't vote
on this but this is also for
consideration is you know are we going
to cap it and move away from we had
discussed last uh meeting with the range
between 200 and 600 with a sliding scale
and move in a different direction to
capping it at 300 to 350. And not that I
don't think that the markers idea with
veterans elderly um in different
communities are not important it's just
we're running out of time. Um, so I
think that's for the next meeting is how
would we that would that look like?
Would we be doing the power model? So
that's like the homework for the next
meeting is considering the power uh the
community empowerment or the provider
empowerment model and what that would
look like when we're looking at markers
for trying to figure out how are we
going to reach this. First thing that
came to mind though is just like a
questionnaire for the community for
these particular providers what they
think might be needed in their
community. Um and maybe this is where we
would go and talk to Larry Leman and
anyone else who are actually doing who
have done these questionnaires or maybe
it's also the department of health. Um
then we can get that information and
figure out how best to allocate in the
provider empowerment model to these
particular places. Okay. So that's what
are the markers that we need first maybe
move to capping it. Dominic, what do you
have to say for us right now?
>> Yes. Good afternoon everyone. So,
originally the department was going to
be presenting a couple of potential
options for today and um but with the
other presentations and with as much
feedback and discussion that people were
having, we opted to instead really just
listen and hear what people wanted to
say. But what I would like to propose is
in the next meeting um what we would
like to do is to present that
information because we had talked about
various aspects including what different
potential sliding scales and percentages
would be. We talked about what potential
um other programs there are that we
could use so that patients wouldn't have
to try to create new documents or have
other barriers to prove their income.
for example, to talk about different
areas where equity is needed, including
social, demographic, geographic areas.
And so, we have a fair amount of that.
But with hearing what what everyone's
saying right now, what I would like to
propose and because we do have to set
the next meeting is give us a little bit
more time because we're also working on
the education piece. And if we could set
this next meeting on the equity for
about a month from now, we can come in
and do a presentation with some of these
different ideas taking into account the
different things people have been
talking about, not just in today's
meeting, but in other meetings and uh uh
that have been occurring and do a
presentation on a couple of different
ideas with regard to what equity could
look like with the program. And part of
the reason I say give us that little bit
of time is so that we can incorporate
what has happened in this meeting and a
couple others that have happened
recently. Um so that we can ensure that
we're we're not just saying hey here's
just one potential way but here are a
couple of potential options and then we
allow for that to be considered for a
while because the thing to remember is
um that the first patients aren't going
to be seen until December is what the
plan is right now and what the goal is.
And so that means we have a few months
to come up with these ideas and with
this the plan on how to use the equity
fund to make sure it truly is as
equitable as we can possibly make it.
And uh and some of the things for
example that have come out today about
you know what are those levels, what
populations, what do we need to do as
far as advertising in you know to ensure
that the word gets out and all of those
sort of things. So I would just like to
propose that and um and because we do we
only have a couple minutes left. I would
suggest for if we say about a month does
that sound good to you Desba and to the
other people who are here and that way
it gives us a little extra time to
prepare those possibilities.
>> I agree and yes thank you. Sorry that we
didn't get around to that, but I guess
maybe it worked out in this way because
then you're getting the information that
you need to, you know, work on the model
presentation that you have that you were
going to do. Um, okay. So, is it okay if
we decide to do the capping or should we
wait until next meeting? What do you
think?
>> I would say wait till the next meeting
for us to be able to present some of the
different possibilities.
>> Okay.
>> And for people to think about it.
>> Yes. So, okay. Before we leave, we got
four minutes. think about capping it at
300 or three 300%. Right? So about 47
$50,000 at this time, right? So anyone
below that would get full 100% coverage
of a treatment. Um it could be less.
Also look at ways in which markers could
possibly help. We have some comments
here. Um, and then just also kind of
thinking about, you know, the power
equity model, like what it would look
like for agency of an individual person
versus a provider saying, "Hey, this is
what my community needs." Um, and then
we can move forward and, you know,
looking forward to um the department's
presentation and then we're we're going
to figure this out. So, thank you so
much for your time. Have a beautiful
afternoon.
Desba, can you set the date?
>> Meeting.
>> Yes. Uh, sorry, the 16th.
>> One month from now would be the 16th.
So, same time, 3 to 5.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, we're looking at June 16th
from 3 to 5 for the next meeting.
>> Yes.
>> And thank you everybody. It really great
to hear people's thoughts and ideas.
Definitely is appreciated and we'll
incorporate what we can into this.
Thank you for your time everyone. Um,
have a great afternoon. Thank you to the
department for your admitting.
Thank you everybody.